So I'd like you to imagine for a moment
أريدك أن تتخيل للحظة
that you're a soldier in the heat of battle.
أنك جندي في قلب المعركة.
Maybe you're a Roman foot soldier or a medieval archer
ربما جندي مشاه روماني أو رامي سهام في القرون الوسطى
or maybe you're a Zulu warrior.
أو ربما أنت محارب زولو.
Regardless of your time and place, there are some things that are constant.
بغض النظر عن الوقت والمكان، هناك بعض الأشياء تبقى ثابتة.
Your adrenaline is elevated,
نسبة الأدرينالين لديك مرتفعة،
and your actions are stemming from these deeply ingrained reflexes,
وأفعالك نابعة من ردود أفعال عميقة الجذور،
reflexes rooted in a need to protect yourself and your side
ردود أفعال متجذرة في حاجتك لحماية نفسك وحماية الجانب الخاص بك
and to defeat the enemy.
وتغلبك على العدو
So now, I'd like you to imagine playing a very different role,
حسنا الآن، أريدك أن تتخيل لعب دور مختلف كليا،
that of the scout.
دور الكشاف.
The scout's job is not to attack or defend.
عمل الكشاف ليس الهجوم أو الدفاع.
The scout's job is to understand.
عمل الكشاف هو الفهم.
The scout is the one going out,
الكشاف هو الشخص الذي يخرج
mapping the terrain, identifying potential obstacles.
يرسم خرائط المنطقة، يحدد العقبات المحتملة.
And the scout may hope to learn that, say, there's a bridge
والكشاف يأمل أن يتعلم، لنقل، هناك جسر
in a convenient location across a river.
في مكان مناسب عبر النهر.
But above all, the scout wants to know what's really there,
لكن قبل هذا، الكشاف يريد أن يعرف ماذا يوجد هناك،
as accurately as possible.
بدقة كبيرة قدر المستطاع.
And in a real, actual army, both the soldier and the scout are essential.
وفي جيش حقيقي، كل من الجندي والكشاف ضروريان.
But you can also think of each of these roles as a mindset --
لكن يمكننا أيضا النظر إلى هذه الأدوار على أساس أنها عقليات.
a metaphor for how all of us process information and ideas
كناية عن كيف أن كل واحد منا يتعامل مع المعلومات والأفكار
in our daily lives.
في حياتنا اليومية.
What I'm going to argue today is that having good judgment,
الذي سوف أتحدث عنه اليوم هو كيف أن التمتع بحكم جيد،
making accurate predictions, making good decisions,
توقع تنبؤات دقيقة، اتخاذ قرارات جيدة،
is mostly about which mindset you're in.
متعلق أساسًا بعقليتك.
To illustrate these mindsets in action,
لتجسيد هذه العقليات في الواقع،
I'm going to take you back to 19th-century France,
سوف آخذكم إلى الوراء في القرن التاسع عشر في فرنسا،
where this innocuous-looking piece of paper
حيث أن قطعة الورق هذه التي تبدو غيرمؤذية تمامًا
launched one of the biggest political scandals in history.
تسببت في واحدة من أكبر الفضائح السياسية في التاريخ.
It was discovered in 1894 by officers in the French general staff.
تم اكتشافها في عام 1894 من قبل ضباط في هيئة الأركان العامة الفرنسية.
It was torn up in a wastepaper basket,
تم تمزيقها ورميها في سلة المهملات،
but when they pieced it back together,
لكن عندما تم جمعها من جديد،
they discovered that someone in their ranks
اكتشفوا أن أحدًا من صفوفهم
had been selling military secrets to Germany.
كان يبيع أسرارًا عسكرية للألمان.
So they launched a big investigation,
فقاموا بفتح تحقيق كبير،
and their suspicions quickly converged on this man,
وشكوكهم بسرعة توجهت نحو هذا الرجل،
Alfred Dreyfus.
ألفريد درايفوس
He had a sterling record,
كان لديه سجل لامع،
no past history of wrongdoing, no motive as far as they could tell.
لم يرتكب أخطاء في الماضي، أو أي دافع واضح لفعل هذا
But Dreyfus was the only Jewish officer at that rank in the army,
لكن درايفوس كان الضابط اليهودي الوحيد بهذه الرتبة في الجيش
and unfortunately at this time, the French Army was highly anti-Semitic.
وللأسف في هذه الوقت، الجيش الفرنسي كان جد معاد للسامية.
They compared Dreyfus's handwriting to that on the memo
قارنوا خط كتابة درايفوس بالخط الموجود في المذكرة
and concluded that it was a match,
وانتهوا إلى وجود تطابق،
even though outside professional handwriting experts
بالرغم من أن محللي الخطوط المحترفين الخواص
were much less confident in the similarity,
كانوا أقل ثقة من تأكد نتائج التشابه.
but never mind that.
لكن دعنا من هذا.
They went and searched Dreyfus's apartment,
لقد ذهبوا وفتشوا شقة درايفوس،
looking for any signs of espionage.
بحثًا عن أي دلائل تُشير إلى التجسس
They went through his files, and they didn't find anything.
فتشوا في كل ملفاته، ولم يجدوا شيئًا.
This just convinced them more that Dreyfus was not only guilty,
لكن هذا أقنعهم أكثر أن درايفوس لم يكن مذنبًا فقط،
but sneaky as well, because clearly he had hidden all of the evidence
لكن محتالاً أيضًا، لأنه من الواضح قام بإخفاء جميع الأدلة
before they had managed to get to it.
قبل أن يتمكنوا من الوصول إليها.
Next, they went and looked through his personal history
بعد ذلك، قاموا بالبحث في تاريخه الشخصي
for any incriminating details.
عن أي تفاصيل مشبوهة.
They talked to his teachers,
تكلموا مع أساتذته،
they found that he had studied foreign languages in school,
ووجدوا أنه قد تعلم لغات أجنبية في المدرسة،
which clearly showed a desire to conspire with foreign governments
ما أظهر بشدة رغبة التآمر مع حكومات أجنبية
later in life.
لاحقًا في حياته.
His teachers also said that Dreyfus was known for having a good memory,
أكد أساتذته كذلك أن درايفوس كان يتمتع بذاكرة جيدة،
which was highly suspicious, right?
ما كان مثيرًا للشبهة، أليس كذلك؟
You know, because a spy has to remember a lot of things.
تعلمون، لأنه جاسوس فعليه تذكر الكثير من الأشياء.
So the case went to trial, and Dreyfus was found guilty.
أحيلت القضية إلى المحكمة، وحكم على درايفوس بالجرم.
Afterwards, they took him out into this public square
بعد ذلك، قاموا بأخذه إلى الساحة العامة
and ritualistically tore his insignia from his uniform
ورمزيًا قاموا بنزع شارته من بذلته العسكرية
and broke his sword in two.
وكسروا سيفه إلى نصفين.
This was called the Degradation of Dreyfus.
وهذا كان يسمى إذلال درايفوس
And they sentenced him to life imprisonment
وحكموا عليه بالسجن المؤبد
on the aptly named Devil's Island,
على الجزيرة المسماة طبقا لفعله، جزيرة الشيطان،
which is this barren rock off the coast of South America.
صخرة مجدبة قبالة سواحل أمريكا الجنوبية.
So there he went, and there he spent his days alone,
إذن هنالك ذهب، وهنالك أمضى أيامه وحيدًا،
writing letters and letters to the French government
يكتب رسائل ورسائل للحكومة الفرنسية
begging them to reopen his case so they could discover his innocence.
متوسلاً إياهم فتح التحقيق مجددًا علهم يكتشفون براءته.
But for the most part, France considered the matter closed.
لكن على العموم، فرنسا اعتبرت أن القضية قد أُغلقت.
One thing that's really interesting to me about the Dreyfus Affair
شيء واحد مثير جدًا بالنسبة لي حول قضية درايفوس
is this question of why the officers were so convinced
هو سؤال لماذا كان الضباط جد متيقنين
that Dreyfus was guilty.
أن درايفوس كان مذنبًا؟
I mean, you might even assume that they were setting him up,
أقصد، أنكم يمكنكم حتى الإعتقاد أنهم كانوا يريدون الإيقاع به،
that they were intentionally framing him.
أنهم أرادوا تدبير مكيدة له.
But historians don't think that's what happened.
لكن المؤرخين لا يعتقدون أن هذا الذي حدث.
As far as we can tell,
ما يمكننا قوله،
the officers genuinely believed that the case against Dreyfus was strong.
هو أن الضباط كانوا متأكدين أن القضية ضد درايفوس كانت قوية.
Which makes you wonder:
الذي يجعلكم تتساءلون:
What does it say about the human mind
ماذا يمكننا القول عن العقل البشري
that we can find such paltry evidence
إذا كانت مجموعة من الأدلة الواهنة
to be compelling enough to convict a man?
كافية للحكم على شخص بالجرم؟
Well, this is a case of what scientists call "motivated reasoning."
حسنًا، هذه هي الحالة التي يطلق عليها العلماء "الإستدلال المدفوع."
It's this phenomenon in which our unconscious motivations,
إنها حالة حيث تكون دوافعنا اللاإرادية،
our desires and fears,
شهواتنا و مخاوفنا،
shape the way we interpret information.
تحدد الطريقة التي نحلل بها المعلومات.
Some information, some ideas, feel like our allies.
بعض المعلومات، بعض الأفكار، نشعر وكأنها حليفتنا.
We want them to win. We want to defend them.
نريدها أن تنجح. تريد أن ندافع عنها.
And other information or ideas are the enemy,
وبعض المعلومات و الأفكار الأخرى وكأنها أعداء لنا،
and we want to shoot them down.
ونريد إسقاطها أرضًا.
So this is why I call motivated reasoning, "soldier mindset."
ولهذا أطلق على الإستدلال المدفوع "عقلية الجندي."
Probably most of you have never persecuted
لم يسبق لأحد منكم على الأرجح
a French-Jewish officer for high treason,
اضطهاد ضابط فرنسي يهودي بسبب الخيانة،
I assume,
أفترض،
but maybe you've followed sports or politics, so you might have noticed
لكن ربما تتبعتم الرياضة أو السياسة، لذا ربما قد لاحظتم
that when the referee judges that your team committed a foul,
أنه إذا أعلن الحكم أن فريقك ارتكب خطأ،
for example,
على سبيل المثال،
you're highly motivated to find reasons why he's wrong.
فسوف تندفع للبحث عن سبب لتبين أن الحكم قد أخطأ.
But if he judges that the other team committed a foul -- awesome!
لكن إذا أعلن أن الفريق الآخر ارتكب خطأ -- رائع !
That's a good call, let's not examine it too closely.
تحكيم رائع، دعونا لا ندقق في الحكم كثيرًا.
Or, maybe you've read an article or a study
أو ربما، قرأتم مقالاً أو دراسة
that examined some controversial policy,
قامت بتحليل موضوع مثير للجدل،
like capital punishment.
مثل عقوبة الإعدام.
And, as researchers have demonstrated,
وأظهر الباحثون في هذه الدراسة،
if you support capital punishment
وكنت أنت من المؤيدين لعقوبة الإعدام
and the study shows that it's not effective,
وأظهرت الدراسة أن الإعدام غير مجد،
then you're highly motivated to find all the reasons
فسوف تكون جد متحمس للبحث عن كل الأسباب
why the study was poorly designed.
لماذا هذه الدراسة لم تكن جيدة بما فيه الكفاية
But if it shows that capital punishment works,
لكن إذا أظهرت أن عقوبة الإعدام مجدية،
it's a good study.
فإذن هي دراسة جيدة.
And vice versa: if you don't support capital punishment, same thing.
وهكذا: إذا لم تؤيد عقوبة الإعدام، فنفس الشيء.
Our judgment is strongly influenced, unconsciously,
إن أحكامنا متأثرةبدرجة كبيرة، بغير وعي منا،
by which side we want to win.
بأي طرف نريده أن يفوز.
And this is ubiquitous.
وهذا في كل شخص منا.
This shapes how we think about our health, our relationships,
هذا يحدد كيف نفكر حول صحتنا، حول علاقاتنا،
how we decide how to vote,
كيف نحدد كيفية التصويت،
what we consider fair or ethical.
ما الذي نعتبره عدلاً أو أخلاقًا.
What's most scary to me about motivated reasoning
والشيء الذي يخيفني كثيرًا حول الاستدلال المدفوع
or soldier mindset,
أو عقلية الجندي،
is how unconscious it is.
هو كيف أنه خارج عن شعورنا
We can think we're being objective and fair-minded
يمكننا الظن أننا موضوعيون ومحايدون
and still wind up ruining the life of an innocent man.
و مع كل هذا ندمر حياة شخص بريء.
However, fortunately for Dreyfus, his story is not over.
ولكن، لحسن حظ درايفوس، فإن قصته لم تنته.
This is Colonel Picquart.
هذا هو الكولونيل "بيكارت"
He's another high-ranking officer in the French Army,
وهو ضابط عالي الرتبة أيضًا في الجيش الفرنسي،
and like most people, he assumed Dreyfus was guilty.
ومثل الكثير من الأشخاص، افترض أن درايفوس كان مذنبًا.
Also like most people in the army, he was at least casually anti-Semitic.
أيضًا مثل الكثير من الجنود، فقد كان معاديًا للسامية أيضا.
But at a certain point, Picquart began to suspect:
لكن لوهلة، "بيكارت" بدأ في الشك:
"What if we're all wrong about Dreyfus?"
"ماذا لو كنا مخطئين تمامًا فيما يتعلق بدرايفوس؟"
What happened was, he had discovered evidence
الشيء الذي حدث، هو أنه قد اكتشف دليلاً
that the spying for Germany had continued,
أن التجسس لصالح الألمان قد استمرت،
even after Dreyfus was in prison.
حتى بعد زج درايفوس في السجن.
And he had also discovered that another officer in the army
واكتشف أيضًا أنه يوجد هنالك ضابط آخر في الجيش
had handwriting that perfectly matched the memo,
طابق خط كتابته ما كتب على المذكرة أيضًا،
much closer than Dreyfus's handwriting.
أكثر تطابقًا من خط كتابة درايفوس.
So he brought these discoveries to his superiors,
فقام بتسليم هذه الاكتشافات لرؤسائه،
but to his dismay, they either didn't care
ولكن في حيرة، إما لم يهتموا لهذا
or came up with elaborate rationalizations to explain his findings,
أو خلق حجج لتأويل تفسيراته،
like, "Well, all you've really shown, Picquart, is that there's another spy
مثل، "كل ما بينته حقيقة، بيكارت، هو أنه يوجد جاسوس آخر
who learned how to mimic Dreyfus's handwriting,
تعلم كيف يقلد خط كتابة درايفوس،
and he picked up the torch of spying after Dreyfus left.
وأكمل عملية التجسس بعدما تم القبض على درايفوس.
But Dreyfus is still guilty."
لكن درايفوس مازال مذنبًا."
Eventually, Picquart managed to get Dreyfus exonerated.
في نهاية المطاف، تمكن "بيكارت" من تبرئة درايفوس.
But it took him 10 years,
لكن هذا تطلب 10 سنوات كاملة،
and for part of that time, he himself was in prison
أمضى خلالها بعض الوقت في السجن هو أيضًا
for the crime of disloyalty to the army.
بتهمة عدم الولاء للجيش.
A lot of people feel like Picquart can't really be the hero of this story
الكثير من الأشخاص ظن أن "بيكارت" لا يمكن أن يكون بطل هذه القصة
because he was an anti-Semite and that's bad, which I agree with.
لأنه كان معاديًا للسامية وهذا سيء، وأنا أؤيد ذلكز
But personally, for me, the fact that Picquart was anti-Semitic
لكن شخصيًا، بالنسبة لي، فكرة أن "بيكارت" كان معادٍ للسامية
actually makes his actions more admirable,
يجعل في الحقيقة أفعاله هذه أكثر إثارة للإعجاب،
because he had the same prejudices, the same reasons to be biased
لأنه كان يتمتع بنفس الأحكام المسبقة، نفس الأسباب ليكون متحيزًا
as his fellow officers,
مثل رفاقه الضباط،
but his motivation to find the truth and uphold it trumped all of that.
لكن دوافعه للبحث عن الحقيقة والتمسك بها أسقطت كل هذا.
So to me,
لهذا بالنسبة لي،
Picquart is a poster child for what I call "scout mindset."
"بيكارت" هو المثال لما أسميه "عقلية الكشاف."
It's the drive not to make one idea win or another lose,
إنها إرادة عدم جعل فكرة تفوز والأخرى تخسر،
but just to see what's really there
لكن فقط لمعرفة ما يحدث حقًا
as honestly and accurately as you can,
بأمانة وصدق قدر المستطاع،
even if it's not pretty or convenient or pleasant.
حتى ولو لم تكن جيدة أو مناسبة أو مثيرة لإعجابه.
This mindset is what I'm personally passionate about.
شخصيًا هذه العقلية تثير شغفي.
And I've spent the last few years examining and trying to figure out
وقد أمضيت البضع سنوات الأخيرة في التحليل محاولةً معرفة
what causes scout mindset.
ما الذي يسبب عقلية الكشاف.
Why are some people, sometimes at least,
لماذا بعض الأشخاص، على الأقل أحيانًا،
able to cut through their own prejudices and biases and motivations
قادرون على تجاهل أحكامهم المسبقة وتحيزهم واندفاعهم،
and just try to see the facts and the evidence
ومحاولة رؤية الحقائق و الأدلة
as objectively as they can?
بأكبر قدر من الموضوعية؟
And the answer is emotional.
والإجابة هي العاطفة.
So, just as soldier mindset is rooted in emotions
فمثلما أن عقلية الجندي متجذرة في عاطفتنا
like defensiveness or tribalism,
كالغرائز الدفاعية أو القبائلية،
scout mindset is, too.
فكذلك عقلية الكشاف.
It's just rooted in different emotions.
إنها متجذرة في عواطفنا.
For example, scouts are curious.
على سبيل المثال، الكشافة فضوليون.
They're more likely to say they feel pleasure
إنهم أكثر ميلاً للقول بأنهم يشعرون بالمتعة
when they learn new information
عند تعلم معارف جديدة
or an itch to solve a puzzle.
أو إذا توجب عليهم حل مشكلة.
They're more likely to feel intrigued when they encounter something
هم أكثر ميلاً للشعور بالافتتان إذا صادفوا شيئًا
that contradicts their expectations.
مخالفًا لتوقعاتهم.
Scouts also have different values.
للكشافة أيضًا قيم مختلفة.
They're more likely to say they think it's virtuous
إنهم يذهبون للقول بأنه من الجيد
to test your own beliefs,
أن تختبر معتقداتك الخاصة،
and they're less likely to say that someone who changes his mind
وأقل ميلاً لوصف شخص غيّر من تفكيره
seems weak.
بأنه شخص ضعيف.
And above all, scouts are grounded,
وفوق هذا، الكشافة أصوليون،
which means their self-worth as a person
ما يعني أن قيمتهم كأشخاص
isn't tied to how right or wrong they are about any particular topic.
ليست متعلقة بموقفهم حيال موضوع معين.
So they can believe that capital punishment works.
فيمكنهم الاعتقاد بأن عقوبة الإعدام مجدية.
If studies come out showing that it doesn't, they can say,
وإذا أظهرت الدراسات أنها ليست مجدية، يمكنهم القول،
"Huh. Looks like I might be wrong. Doesn't mean I'm bad or stupid."
"هاه، يبدو أنني ربما كنت مخطئ. ولا يعني أني سيء أو غبي."
This cluster of traits is what researchers have found --
هذه المجموعة من الصفات هي ما وجده الباحثون --
and I've also found anecdotally --
ووجدته أنا أيضًا تناقلاً --
predicts good judgment.
تساعد في التنبؤ بالأحكام الجيدة.
And the key takeaway I want to leave you with about those traits
والفكرة التي أريد أن أتركها في أذهانكم حول هذه الصفات
is that they're primarily not about how smart you are
أنها أساسًا ليست حول درجة ذكائك
or about how much you know.
أو حول مقدار معرفتك.
In fact, they don't correlate very much with IQ at all.
في الحقيقة، ليست تتناسب مطلقًا مع درجة الذكاء.
They're about how you feel.
بل هي حول ما تشعر به.
There's a quote that I keep coming back to, by Saint-Exupéry.
هناك اقتباس أظل أردده، للكاتب "ساينت إكسبيري".
He's the author of "The Little Prince."
وهو كاتب "الأمير الصغير."
He said, "If you want to build a ship,
قال: "إذا أردت بناء سفينة،
don't drum up your men to collect wood and give orders
لا تحشد الرجال لجمع الخشب وإعطاء الأوامر
and distribute the work.
وتوزيع المهام.
Instead, teach them to yearn for the vast and endless sea."
لكن علمهم أن يحنوا إلى البحر الواسع اللامتناهي."
In other words, I claim,
بتعبير آخر، أزعم
if we really want to improve our judgment as individuals
إذا أردنا حقا تحسين أحكامنا كأفراد
and as societies,
وكمجتمعات،
what we need most is not more instruction in logic
ما نحتاجه بشدة، ليس المزيد من الدروس في المنطق
or rhetoric or probability or economics,
أو الخطابة أو الاحتمالات أو الاقتصاد،
even though those things are quite valuable.
بالرغم من أن كل هذه الأشياء قيّمة جدًا.
But what we most need to use those principles well
ولكم ما نحتاجه لاستعمال هذه المبادئ جيدًا
is scout mindset.
هو عقلية الكشاف.
We need to change the way we feel.
علينا أن نغير كيفية شعورنا.
We need to learn how to feel proud instead of ashamed
علينا أن نتعلم كيف نحس بالفخر لا بالعار
when we notice we might have been wrong about something.
عندما نلاحظ أننا ربما كنا مخطئين حول شيء ما.
We need to learn how to feel intrigued instead of defensive
علينا أن نتعلم كيف نشعر بالافتتان بدلاً من أن نكون دفاعيين
when we encounter some information that contradicts our beliefs.
عندما نصادف معلومات متعارضة مع اعتقاداتنا.
So the question I want to leave you with is:
إذًا فالسؤال الذي أريد أن أتركه لكم هو:
What do you most yearn for?
ما الذي تتوقون إليه كثيرًا؟
Do you yearn to defend your own beliefs?
هل تتوقون إلى الدفاع عن معتقداتكم الخاصة؟
Or do you yearn to see the world as clearly as you possibly can?
أو تتوقون إلى رؤية العالم بوضوح قدر المستطاع؟
Thank you.
شكرًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)